Mary G. Ziegler Papers 010
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Mary G. Ziegler Papers
1950-1980
DCPL Special Collections - MLK Library
Ziegler, Mary G.
010
9 Boxes
3.5 Linear feet
Biographical / Historical
Mary G. Ziegler was an educator, beginning work at the District Training School for the Feeble Minded (later Forest Haven Asylum) in 1928 as a teacher and retiring in 1962 as the principal. The school was established in 1925 at the Fort Meade Army Base as a farm colony and hospital for the training of persons with intellectual disabilities. In 1961 D.C. government honored the work of Ziegler by dedicating and opening the Mary G. Ziegler School.
Custodial History
Donor unknown.
Scope and Contents
The materials in this collection relate to Mary Ziegler's career as an educator of persons with intellectual disabilities at the District Training School for the Feeble Minded in Laurel, Maryland (later Forest Haven Asylum). Materials include photographs of activities and events; publications on the education of persons with intellectual disabilities; press releases; programs; a newsletter; correspondence; awards; published books; and certificates. Of note are seven scrapbooks created by Zeigler on the District Training School dated 1924 to the 1960s; including clippings, photographs, programs, invitations, letters, and other memorabilia.
Arrangement
Processed without series.
Education; Urban renewal; Gentrification; Public schools; Intellectual disability; Educators; Photographs; Newsletters; Correspondence; Ephemera
- Series 1
  - Activities for... Trainables, Undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Awards, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Brochures, 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brochures, 1953-1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Certificates of appreciation, 1959-1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Client-attorney correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Clippings, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Center News and Views, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Connecticut Avenue Association, Undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Certification for flag flying over the Capitol, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Forest Haven, 1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Friends of Forest Haven, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Government publications, 1966-1967 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - History of the D.C. Training School, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Letters of appreciation, 1961-1962 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Mental retardation newspaper campaign, 1960s (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Photographs, Undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Press releases, 1970-1981 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Press releases, 1970-1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Press releases, 1970-1981 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Ziegler School Dedication, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Ziegler School Dedication, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Ziegler School Dedication plaque, Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Oversized colorized clipping, Undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - District Training School (DST) scrapbook, 1924-1942 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - DST scrapbook (primarily photos), 1924-1954 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - DST scrapbook, 1943-1954 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - DST scrapbook, 1950s (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - DST scrapbook, 1955-1959 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - DST scrapbook, 1957-1958 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - DST scrapbook, 1960s (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Certificate of Merit, Undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Cortazzo, 1963 (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - Department of Health, January 1967 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Louis E. Rosenzweig and Julia Long - Understanding and Teaching the Dependent Retarded Child - Darien - Connecticut: The Education Publishing Corporation, 1960 (Box 9, Folder 3)